<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-04-26T14:12:05+00:00</updated><id>https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Home of an Artist - Nilesh Babulal Jain</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Astronomy Facts</title><link href="https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2021/videos/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Astronomy Facts"/><published>2021-11-16T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-16T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2021/videos</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2021/videos/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="why-we-look-up"><strong>Why we look up?</strong></h2> <p><strong>Rogue Planets - What Are They?</strong></p> <ul> <li>Without Sun, they’re basically orphans, cast away, molten but frozen.</li> </ul> <p>Now you may ask, what’s a planet? What defines it? And why your favorite Pluto isn’t one? Blame Neil Degrasse Tyson for figuring out.</p> <p>You ask, how did the moon form or the sun form? Or how old is our galaxy or our whole universe which is believed to be 14 billion years old, is it true? What’s beyond the farthest we can go? Just generating some hype there. In this blog, I want people to know the basics of astronomy and looking up so that they can be astonished by what’s up in the sky and not take it for granted.</p> <p><strong>Stars</strong></p> <ul> <li>You see the sun? Yeah, that giant yellow ball? Oh, It’s not yellow - the sun is white in color but we’ll come to that.</li> <li>Your beloved sun was formed after rising from the ashes of stars.</li> <li>When a giant/big star dies it creates an explosion and that’s called a “Supernova”.</li> <li>Also, a star doesn’t look like what your teacher drew you in kindergarten.</li> <li>Oxygen, carbon, calcium, iron all burned fiery in stars.</li> <li>There’s a reason we’re made of star stuff. All of this is inside us.</li> <li>Remnants of Kepler, Socrates, or even Stephen Hawking, you might just be breathing those atoms.</li> <li>You know that big star you call sun? It was formed after 7 billion years of the universe created.</li> <li>Newton Halley (the guy behind Haley’s comet) made the first star map of the sky of the southern hemisphere.</li> <li>Also, some stars are already dead by the time their light reaches us and we’re able to see. What do I mean by that? <ul> <li>Pssst. You’re seeing the past always.</li> <li>Moon - You’re seeing 1 second into the past.</li> <li>Sun - 8 mins into the past.</li> <li>Neptune - 4 hours</li> <li>A Light year is 9.46 trillion miles</li> <li>And our nearest brightest neighbor, Proxima Centauri to the sun is 4 light years away.</li> <li>Psst. Coming back to the stars.</li> </ul> </li> <li>You are looking at the night sky. You look at some stars bright and some very dim. <ul> <li>It may be because some stars are closer to you or some stars are far but very bigger.</li> <li>Or it can be 2 or more stars dancing around giving us the illusion of one bright star.</li> <li>You just have to look closely. Get your telescopes on.</li> </ul> </li> <li>90% of the atoms in the universe and 2/3 of your body are Hydrogen.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Where Everything Comes From?</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>Earth</strong> <ul> <li>First, Let’s Talk about our beloved planet - <a href="link">watch this video</a> to see how big ;) our planet is.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Constellations</strong> - Patterns in the sky to help understand similar patterns.</li> <li><strong>Comet</strong> - Message from god Haha - NO. It’s mostly made of ice and rocks and if they come near the sun. <ul> <li>They lose a part and what remains after heating, is what you see. The trailing gas bcoz the sun bakes it.</li> <li>After too much heating, evaporation happens and then comes your Fearful “Asteroid”.</li> </ul> </li> <li>A meteoroid are small rocks that fall to the earth after the earth’s atmosphere beats it to the ground.</li> <li>How did the moon form? Turns out our planet collided with another planet and all the debris formed slowly turned into the moon over billions of years. <ul> <li>But there are multiple theories to this. Moon was 10x closer back then. Much brighter. As Moon is responsible for tidal waves. Seas formed. Tides were 1k higher than.</li> <li>Tidal Friction pushed moon away.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Talking about moons. We have only 1. Jupiter has 53 moons + 26 long due to be named. But Saturn beats it with its tally of 82.</li> <li>A cluster is a group of stars/galaxies together.</li> <li>The Virgo cluster contains our beloved Milky Way Galaxy and the neighboring galaxy “AndroMeda” which is only 2.5 million light years away. <ul> <li>But don’t worry they are going to meet each other one day forming the best dance the universe may ever see.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Our Earth was formed from gas &amp; dust from the sun. Ancient forests grew and died and sank. Then you got coal.</li> <li>Ghost Stars - Stars which are dead by the time their light reaches earth.</li> <li>Earth’s atmosphere bends the rays of sunlight like a sens so we see the image before it is actually there hence you can experience the sunrise and sunset.</li> </ul> <p><strong>What the Universe Consists of?</strong></p> <ul> <li>90% Hydrogen (H) as previously mentioned.</li> <li>After H, He (Helium) is the 2nd most abundant - 50x than all other elements combined.</li> <li>Helium is in the sun’s corona. And Also the Greek sun god. That’s crazy.</li> <li>Now to Lithium - 3rd largest with 3 protons in its nucleus.</li> <li>Lithium gets destroyed by all nuclear reactions.</li> <li>Carbon - Forged in the core of stars same as oxygen.</li> <li>10% of Earth’s crust is Aluminium.</li> <li>Titanium - Military aircraft, strong metal.</li> <li>Titan - Saturn’s Largest moon.</li> <li>First atomic bomb had “Uranium” as an active ingredient.</li> <li>Plutonium in “Nagasaki” bomb.</li> </ul> <p>More coming soon… Adding more in coming week. &lt;!–</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <video src="/assets/video/pexels-engin-akyurt-6069112-960x540-30fps.mp4" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" autoplay="" controls=""/> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <video src="/assets/video/pexels-engin-akyurt-6069112-960x540-30fps.mp4" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" controls=""/> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A simple, elegant caption looks good between video rows, after each row, or doesn't have to be there at all. </div> <p>It does also support embedding videos from different sources. Here are some examples:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jNQXAC9IVRw" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/524933864?h=1ac4fd9fb4&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> </div> --&gt; </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog-posts"/><category term="astronomy"/><category term="facts"/><category term="science"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Wanna know some curious facts about our Universe?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Eric Barker Blog - Bakadesuyo.com</title><link href="https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2021/jupyter-notebook/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Eric Barker Blog - Bakadesuyo.com"/><published>2021-11-16T12:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-16T12:57:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2021/jupyter-notebook</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2021/jupyter-notebook/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="eric-barkers-way"><strong>Eric Barker’s way</strong></h1> <p><strong>Debating &amp; Arguing</strong></p> <ul> <li>“Once we think we know someone we stop paying attention” To update we need conflicts..</li> <li>If you’re arguing too little - may be you’re avoiding problems. You can’t put emotions aside - they’re always there no matter what. Some are just too sure they’re right and incapable of listening and just masters of assumptions.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Boredom</strong></p> <ul> <li>It’s a signal, a motivator to get your ass up to do something meaningful with your life.</li> <li>To get curious - Stop going into your head again and again and dive deeper into what you’re good at and whatever you’re currently doing.</li> <li>Find Meaning:- Ask yourself why you’re doing what you’re doing.</li> <li>Make it yours:- Follow a script, a disciplined scheduled but make sure you own it.</li> <li>The goldilocks zone:- Make it a challenge, bet with your friends, announce it on social media. Test your abilities and lose yourself in the moment.</li> <li>Boredom tries to guide you towards a better life and gives your brain signals that there is something that you can spend your time on.</li> <li>Weak attention skills, more sensation seeking &amp; lack of self control people are more prone to boredom. Guess I have all those.</li> <li>It’s an alarm. To wake up.</li> <li>It has something to tell us. Make better life choices by responding to it. Be the authors of the lives we want to live.</li> <li>Boredom is weird. An awkward mix of low mood with a shaking urgency to do something. A nervous itch in your bones as your soul makes a noise like a deflating tire. Researchers found it’s the fourth most common negative feeling, just behind exhaustion, frustration and indifference.</li> <li>And these days it’s gotten so bad we actually fear boredom. And we’re not crazy. The negatives of boredom are worse than you think and I have the receipts to prove it. As you may have guessed, the more bored you are in a given day, the more calories you consume. Studies also show boredom increases risky decision making. It makes you more likely to drink and smoke. It also has a connection to more socially carcinogenic habits like vandalism, delinquency and outright criminal behavior. (Yes, “killing time” may lead to “doing time.”)</li> <li>But there’s a twist: boredom can actually be a good thing. Yes, really. Diving into the research I found that boredom is, well, kinda fascinating.</li> <li>We often blame the world for creating our boredom but, as we’ll find, it’s much more about the choices we make and how we respond to life. The upside is there are things we can do to address this problem — and we can learn a lot about the human condition in the process. Monotonous tasks are boring because they demand our attention but at the same time fail to fully occupy our mental resources. To overcome it you have to basically be mindful. Stepping back from your emotions and becoming immersed in what you’re doing.</li> <li>The point is to redirect your attention from the thoughts and feelings about the activity and get closer to the activity itself.</li> <li>How do we do that? Curiosity. Go deeper into the activity versus getting lost in your thoughts. We get passive and expect the world to make us curious. Sorry, that’s your job. Because when you’re curious, you pretty much can’t be bored.</li> <li>I Love this “ We need to feel like we’re on a mission. Famed psychologist Viktor Frankl felt meaning was central to human lives. When we don’t have it “the existential vacuum manifests itself mainly in a state of boredom.” So when we’re bored we usually turn to deep purposeful action, right?</li> <li>Wrong, we turn to our phones – and that rarely works. Why? We trick ourselves into thinking that mere engagement equals meaning. We want to use our skills and accomplish something we can take pride in, but the internet is often empty calories. Taking yet another ride on the unspirational hamster wheel of novelty doesn’t provide the bedrock of purpose. The internet is a combover for your life problems, death by 1,000 notifications.”</li> <li>And this has longer term consequences. It atrophies our meaning-making muscles. We become passive containers waiting to be filled, rather than bold creators of meaning. We forget what we’re passionate about because we expect the world to hand purpose to us. As Frankl wrote, “When a person can’t find a deep sense of meaning, they distract themselves with pleasure.”</li> <li>Some things we have to do aren’t inherently boring but they’re made boring by circumstance. You know what that circumstance is?</li> <li>Well, you have to keep reading to find out. Yes, you have to. I’m not asking you to keep reading; I’m ordering you to keep reading. You have no choice.</li> <li>I’m kidding, of course. But that’s the answer right there. Un-boring stuff can be made boring when we’re forced to do it…</li> </ul> <p><strong>Mismatch Between Skills And Challenge</strong></p> <ul> <li>When we have something to do but it’s not challenging enough, we get bored. And when it’s too challenging, we feel overwhelmed and get bored. What we want is that balance where an activity is testing us. Where success feels possible but not guaranteed. That’s when we experience “flow.” That’s optimal engagement – and it feels great.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Psychology</strong></p> <ul> <li>Life is wonderful, then something bad happens and it sullies everything that came before it.</li> <li>We all have contamination sequences but for some people it’s a setback they never recover from.</li> <li>A fall from grace. They let it set the tone for the rest of their tale</li> <li>And this contamination sequence leads to a Contamination Story.</li> <li>Their personal narrative is about as uplifting as the Necronomicon.</li> <li>These people seem stuck in a loop.</li> <li>Instead of learning from the past and moving on, they relive this sequence, almost as if they are trying to get it right the next time – but never do.</li> <li>You know people like this. They date the same kinds of awful people, get fired from jobs for the same reasons.</li> <li>Their contamination sequence is a mental biohazard that leads you to shake your head and say, “They never learn.”</li> <li>Their life is the symptom but the story is the disease.</li> <li>They’re running cognitive malware in their heads and eventually their lives come to resemble the dark poem of downfall that is their story.</li> <li>Carpe the hell out of the diem.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Friendships</strong></p> <ul> <li>Friends are imp. There is nothing surprising about them but it is critical for happiness. Friends shouldn’t make sense.</li> <li>We thank others/strangers for the stuff they do for us but how often do you thank your close friends and family for the stuff they do?</li> <li>You know those friends where even if you don’t see them for a long time the feelings are There those awesome friendships.</li> <li>It’s about sharing emotional exp and events.</li> <li>What you went in trying times &amp; happy times. Who opened up, asked for advice.</li> <li>That’s how quality relations are built.</li> </ul> <p><strong>On Surviving or Living a Healthy Life:</strong></p> <ul> <li>Eat less often - a surefire way to stay healthy longer.</li> <li>Aging is caused by DNA damage. Calorie restriction extends life in almost every organism studied.</li> <li>Most centenarians eat more veggies and whole grains, less meat, dairy &amp; sugar.</li> <li>Smoking takes 10 years off but the combined effect of not exercising at all and feeling that you’re healthy when you’re not at all can take as much as 23 years.</li> <li>Improve diet &amp; exercise &amp; you’ll live a long way. Everyone knows.</li> <li>Laughing and being happy can also lead to a good life if not longer.</li> <li>Read about Metformin Drug.</li> <li>Death is not the greatest loss in life. The greatest is what dies inside us. What never came out.</li> <li>Remove toxic people, relationships, thoughts and see how meaningful or empty life will become. That’s when you restart. Reenergize.</li> <li>This is all data, studies, years of research speaking and not only that but a lot of ancient texts &amp; religions follow this. It’s better than our current life if we followed all isn’t it?</li> <li>Why not learn what the old have already learned? Why not practice what the researchers have already learned?</li> <li>When we focus on making life better for others, we make our lives better too. We create better stories, we help build a better life.</li> <li>So if you’re not happy with your story, there’s time to restructure &amp; rewrite it. Benefit in the negative.</li> <li>They taught me that people have reasons to do what they do &amp; you can’t help it &amp; you have to move past it.</li> <li>Remembering your days are numbered helps you live a better and more meaningful life.</li> </ul> <p><strong>On Awe:</strong></p> <ul> <li>“Awe arouses altruism.”</li> <li>And we need this feeling as we age.</li> <li>Children’s brains are alive with connections but post-adolescence a lot of those pathways – and that vibrance – get pruned.</li> <li>We go from wonder to wither. Our beliefs congeal and harden. Our consciousness gets narrow.</li> <li>The day-to-day becomes teeth-achingly banal and we fail to dream.</li> <li>Without a bit of breathtaking wonder, you lose things. Like your soul.</li> <li>Andrew Newberg, a neuroscientist at Thomas Jefferson University, has done studies showing awe reduces activity in the default mode network of your brain.</li> <li>You know what else does that? Religious experiences and LSD. Awe is a spiritual reset button.</li> <li>Wait a second… Did I just say we need awe to feel like kids again and then compare awe to LSD? Yeah.</li> <li>Leading developmental psychologist Alison Gopnik says there is a lot of overlap between the wonder and joy of children’s minds and psychedelic experiences.</li> <li>In fact, as she told Michael Pollan: “The short summary is, babies and children are basically tripping all the time.”</li> <li>The word “awesome” gets thrown around a lot these days but we’re talking about real awe.</li> <li>The moments that make your heart race, your hair stand on end and literally take your breath away.</li> <li>When we’re at the precipice of unbounded delight, speechless and dumbstruck in appreciative wonder.</li> <li>Those uncanny things that make you gasp, like the Grand Canyon, the Taj Mahal or your spouse actually apologizing.</li> <li>You try and describe the feeling in words but it comes out like Charlie Brown’s teacher talking.</li> <li>Studies show that second only to feeling cold, awe is the most common cause of goosebumps. It’s the seventh emotion.</li> <li>Previously, psychologists said there were only six emotions: happiness, sadness, anger, fear, surprise and disgust.</li> <li>But awe is so powerful and so unique it qualifies as number seven.</li> <li>All emotions have an evolutionary purpose. Fear is very useful because of its wonderful “not-getting-eaten-by-bears” effect.</li> <li>But what the heck is awe good for? What’s its function? Bringing us together. Awe is the “ultimate collective emotion.” It smacks us back to our factory settings of togetherness.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Extras:</strong></p> <ul> <li>I did a fun experiment on my phone.</li> <li>For about more than a year, I kept changing logos of all the apps Instagram, WhatsApp. But I only slightly changed the logo of YouTube and Twitter which was an older version of the logo.</li> <li>Also, I kept installing new apps or deleting some apps to change their position in my phone every 2-3 weeks. You know why memes save the world? Because we all feel the same way or relate to it. And the same is possible in this experiment.</li> <li>It’s about how your brain is addicted to that logo and position. It’s a hot spot and if you change it. It feels weird. But then again it understands this is the new position to get addicted to.</li> <li>And I kept on changing the positions until I was no more addicted. That’s a lie. I gave up. I uninstalled Instagram. I use it on the web just to post on 2minuteai and multiple channels.</li> <li>The main scene I would like to say is our brain wants to go back to that same place where it last felt good. It associates it with not just the app or the reels inside but also the logo and position where it’s appearing on your phone. Also, if you uninstalled the addicted app, notice how you unlock your phone searching for it again. Super Craving like a drug.</li> <li>One more thing.. it really doesn’t matter what rubbish logo the Insta ppl design. You will get used to it. Same as you get used to seeing your friend clean shaved after a decade. It looks alien at first but then you adapt. Don’t even know if all these experiments make sense or not but they’re fun.</li> <li>One time I told someone to find WhatsApp on my phone they couldn’t find. I guess they’re name blind. Only can see logos.</li> <li>I want to extend this further by changing the app names also and see how fucked up the brain gets.</li> <li>My App Recommendations: Skysafari, skyacademy, skymap; downdog yoga, lojong, quantum, universe; radio garden, deepstash, neo travel your mind, Kickstarter; kahoot, khan academy, insight timer, forest; feedly; ankidroid, edx, pushbullet, let’s meditate, medito, mind tools; presently, todoist, Microsoft to-do, castbox (some podcasts rarely), clubhouse (bookish club); for fun learning(telegram, twitter, reddit, insta, discord, slack); smart voice recorder - pure ranting (emotional as well as angry), loud singing, recording stuff for future me; strava - cycling track; moon+ reader - books when I need it offline; and literally more than a thousand apps installed and uninstalled but these stayed. The internet is making smart people smarter and dumb people dumber. My apps are mostly focused on yoga, meditation, science, and space.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog-posts"/><category term="science"/><category term="hacks"/><category term="blog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My takeaways after reading all his blogs and twitter]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why we understand Psychology differently</title><link href="https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2021/math/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why we understand Psychology differently"/><published>2021-10-20T15:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-20T15:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2021/math</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2021/math/"><![CDATA[<p>Deleted this blog as it didn’t add any meaning to life.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog-posts"/><category term="psychology"/><category term="fun"/><category term="science"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Know a bit about Psychology from a fun experiment]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Imagination the AI we need</title><link href="https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2021/distill/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Imagination the AI we need"/><published>2021-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2021/distill</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2021/distill/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="one-shot-imagination">One Shot Imagination</h1> <p><strong>The first time</strong>, George Mallory at the age of 8, imagined how it would feel like, look like when he would be traveling the toughest natural peak on the planet earth - Everest. He had already imagined himself reaching on the top, he just had to go there now. He had done a lot of school wall climbs and climbing here and there small peaks under 5000ft and everyone had noticed about his special skills of climbing, mountaineering. By the time he was 21 he had already completed more than 17 climbs above 6000ft some even going up to 16000ft but never anything above that. Everest is almost the double of that standing at 29k. There were numerous problems during that time - there was less equipment, less expertise and only sherpas could guide you till the base camp at 21k, and from there for each phase at 24k 26k and final summit, there would be innumerable challenges.</p> <p>Did he make it or not? is not the question. He imagined, visualized every day being at Mount Everest even before he ever saw it, running countless permutations and visualizing the circumstances, the beauty, nature, and the dangers. The heavenly beauty is what surrounded his imagination. In an interesting book written on the same by <strong>Jeffery archer - paths of glory</strong> show this at every pathway to the imagination that George Mallory oughted for.</p> <p>We know the power of it all, and we know thousands of examples from <strong>JK rowling, charlie Chaplin to Mickey Mouse, Jonathan Nolan</strong>. Somehow our <strong>Beautiful Imaginative Imagination</strong> gets overshadowed by the daily mundane tasks, routine, and set goals. I’m also reading the same stuff from the <strong>power of your subconscious mind, power of now, thinking fast and slow</strong>, suggesting to change the way you live and focus on imagining beauty in life and you’ll attract a beauty. <strong>Chase those imaginative goals</strong>. Remember that quote - <strong>reach for the moon, you’ll end up with the stars</strong>?. You do want to end up being a star.</p> <p>Trying to fix my broken specs and inserting the broken temples into the hinges and tightening the screws and, managed to take a look at the outside world while the frames hang in the air, I glanced outside and see the beauty. <strong>How often do you see the beauty outside?</strong> The bird’s beauty, the animals’ beauty, the thing that is appreciated only when you’re in a nature trail. Here <strong>Lord Krishna</strong> Shows up and gives me some lessons about caring, humility, the importance of wind, food, water for living beings other than humans from <strong>Bhagavad Gita</strong>.</p> <p>My personal favorites are <strong>pigeons and elephants</strong>. If you could read my mind now, you could see - lord krishna in my imagination telling me what to do, what not to imagine, basically he’s putting things in my mind - maybe I’m brain washed or hallicunating, god knows, and another person in my head is saying lord cannot be the reason for anything it is just your Karam and the fruit. Bygod. When I turned 9, elephants were still able to roam the streets of Mumbai freely - not free but at least they were not in an open area in a zoo. <strong>PETA tried, unsuccessful</strong>. I would manage to see from the window of my house if an elephant had come by and certainly the jingle bells around the elephant’s neck would awake everyone to witness the elephant, of this big size and how cute it is. Some would donate money just with a stick from the first floor to the elephant handler(I will never say, owner). I was on the third floor and dad had already kept the arrangements for me to sit on the elephant and that is when my love for them started. Only when I grew up did I reiterate my thoughts and learning more about them in every possible way, not just research on the internet but offline experiments in zoos, old libraries, and their stories dating 200 years back. Pigeons on the other hand are more sweet, colorful and innocent. I have seen many pigeons grow over the span of many years, taking shelter in our window space, just in exchange for us to get to see them, feed them. Whenever me and dad went for a walk in the morning, at chowpatty beach, we would never forget to give them desi chickpeas and in return they would fly in circles with their group in perfect alignment with the blue sky and the sea and sand.</p> <p>There have been unfortunate incidents as well, once I was returning from my usual teaching stint at walkeshwar and noticed an injured bird, immediately called a person I had contact of and he helped it out quickly though the pigeon was bloody.</p> <p>Second time, it happened again.. almost the same spot near my college bus stop but this time that man couldn’t pick up the phone. The black and blue pigeon started walking dangerously towards the divider, this is the most awful road to cross, it tried to cross, I imagined what it was trying to do, did it know what it was doing? Obviously but we cannot really know about what they thought..</p> <p>I immediately thought let’s leave it to the pigeon guy who is just 200 meters away. The pigeon somehow reached on the top of divider and then it climbed down to cross the other half to reach with his buddies.</p> <p>There were crazy ass trucks and fast cars on the beachfront stretch, I picked it up quickly and now it started flapping very fast and strong, so I think this is my fault that I didn’t hold on to her tightly, She slipped out of my hands and in one more step she got crushed underneath the trucks tires.</p> <p>I miss them sadly, not because they are not here on the streets, but not in the jungles and I don’t even know if jungles are safe anymore. Wildfires can happen any stupid time. When you do something more often and you give your time more to it, you become that and that’s something everyone knows. If you imagine more, picture more.. you’d be able to have a more creative mind?</p> <p>So how much should you feel? To be able to help them, or anyone. Is there a threshold of studying on a topic? Mr. gates study about 4-5 books on each topic until he gains a good grasp of the topic but when do you start applying and helping people? What’s the set rule or percentage or time when you should help people. Coz you have to share it at one point or another right? In some form otherwise why study in the first place?</p> <p>Also what is the effective way to write and reach your audience? before sounding naive and obtuse to them and you lose your views and let’s say your philosophical neurons are asking you to publish something about the topic at hand before a set deadline… Turns out there’s a solution. The <strong>37% rule</strong>.</p> <p>Imagine your deadline is two weeks from now and you have to write something great about Brains without sounding as I said “Stupid” and without stating the obvious? Your best strategy is to Read 37% of something really hard and be able to combine your expertise in story writing to frame it in a way you save the day. It’s the most optimal road to not losing your views and also having the knowledge in your head.</p> <p>More on this later - This is just my variant of the <strong>37 rule</strong>. There are 1000 variations of the rule to bend it your way and get that 37% chance. Imagine 37% of animals, birds just vanish away from our earth. What would be the reason behind them leaving? Did they find a much better ecosystem much suitable than our habitable planet? Oh I know this- they might have met their parents and family members who are huge in size so they are 63% of others - Susssshh… If they did meet their family, they would be here.</p> <p>Is that what happened to dinosaurs? – Whaaaattt.. are you naturally stupid or inclined towards it. You’re on this mission with me. Save the animals. <strong>Avengers. Assemble</strong> We burn through warm holes and explore various universes and we don’t find them yet. A population of 37% of all animals and birds is huge and could be easily spotted considering they are together. We ask the other half about their loved ones or friends and they have no clue about it, they blame us… we don’t know yet rightfully or not. Maybe the Thanos snap didn’t work properly and it wipes 37 of the population?</p> <p>Just when I am talking about birds and animals, I take a break and my niece is watching a video on monkeys and how they were caged by a businessman in a fictional video and then sold for profit to show the cleverness of the Business guy… What kind of sorcery is this? Whatever you’re learning, somehow everything goes towards it? I was learning from a new course yesterday and my friend after a long time happened to call me and out of nowhere a topic which is the whole part of the course shows up in our conversation and he talks exactly the principles and techniques showed in the course. Mindfuck Infinity.</p> <p>I just saw my old short stories when I used to write after my senior year of school, and I must say the imaginative power of that kid compared to now kid is brilliant. That kid drew up dark endings and thrillers and no rhymed poems, Strategies in Bioweapons, Harassment, and Hunger, all of these without reading a single book, all of the power of imagination.</p> <p>Imagination doesn’t need anything, Sitting here, I can look out the video, visualize my body shrinking itself to escape from the iron grill window and flying to the opposite building’s top and then going into someone’s refrigerator to freak them out.</p> <p>There was this workshop - it was a 10 in 1 workshop, So in 1 day there were 1-hour workshops, this gentleman who handled the copyright laws and trademark laws for Apple and saves them millions of dollars gets us into a visualization state. Visualization is a sub-part of Imagination. It’s a combination of guided meditation, visualization, and of course peer pressure.</p> <p>I’ll tell you how, He started with 5 mins of breathing exercise to relax all of us… then he asked us to imagine going home right now with whatever vehicle you want to go into but not the usual ones…</p> <p>So you have to create your own vehicle to reach home in time otherwise your house will be bombed. Now once you reach there you have to open the refrigerator and smell the muskmelon fruit - I did smell it, feel it, felt the coldness of the fruit in my hand and then there were these pretenders when asked by the host if you’re able to smell…. they replied yes yes when everyone else had finished visualizing. Can’t describe properly, you can always spot a fake when you see it with experience, can’t you? only 30% of the attendees were able to visualize when I asked the majority in a poll answered by 581 people and that didn’t seem like that when asked.. your peer pressure kicking in. So what’s happening here? We weren’t able to visualize and on top of that we feel embarrassed that we couldn’t visualize. 2 in 1 shame</p> <p>Turns out all of them had aphantasia - Naah not really. My theory is that there is a neural pathway that needs to connect to all the networks and form images, so to create one image you need pixels from all synapses and something is blocking that transfer to happen or some pixels are missing and you’re unable to get the bigger picture. Another theory is people are good at visualization audio or text stories in their heads, so maybe the rest 70% of the crowd was divided into audio viz and text viz, some people are good at both of them. You can visualize audio lyrics or songs in your head, right? Creating new gibberish lyrics but to make it into a new song that works with any rhythm or music and sing it loud?</p> <p><strong>For Programmers</strong> Hey quora, quora you aint my dora Reddit is our esposa, go find yourself another senora Tiktok a copy of Dubsmash, stackoverflow is the only aura. Darkness is our IDE, Errors are the light. We don’t want to wake up, so keep debugging on flight. 1 semicolon no worries, solved and 999 more errors to endurite. To Burn your RAM, PC, gotta run android studio. Learn new concepts, fire up an Indian in a youtube video. Getting rid of the wrist syndrome, drinking coffee with pistachio. Prof Andrew Ng, Don’t worry if you don’t know Talk is cheap, Code me and show Writing code with frustation, like surviving without milk of cow Senior developer asks who wrote the code, hide yourself now. Last one was spoiled over, so see you when I caw like a crow</p> ]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="artificial"/><category term="imagination"/><category term="dreams"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Is it a dream or a thought, Let's Explore]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Living with the wires</title><link href="https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2020/github-metadata/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Living with the wires"/><published>2020-03-23T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-23T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2020/github-metadata</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2020/github-metadata/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="inhibition-"><strong>Inhibition .</strong></h1> <h1 id="lyingggg-in-my-bed-i-think-of-you"><strong>Lyingggg… In my bed I think of you…</strong></h1> <p>Caught up in circles… there is nothing new…..flashbacks.. warm nights… almost left behind… I picture this every morning and I think of you… sleeping with wires is a dream come true.. <em>(Time after time)</em></p> <h2 id="sleep-disruption-due-to-poor-inhibition-response-or-anxiety"><strong>Sleep disruption due to poor Inhibition response or anxiety?</strong></h2> <p>When it comes to sleep, People are amazing. It is incredible how much they can sleep, anytime, anywhere in any position. Everyone has different sleep lifecycles, and they mostly follow it though it may be unfortunate enough to affect their circadian rhythm. I mean only stupid people sleep before 11.30, right? Taking a farther look down into our body, we discover the organs that help function and govern everything happening inside us. It’s intricate delicateness &amp; the simple commands are mesmerizing enough to know how natural this body seems and works. But what if all these were untrue in one basic sense - that you couldn’t feel it, there is no natural sense of your existence, and your only mighty existence is in someone’s vague memory, and that is fading away too. Feeling natural, calm, peaceful, composed is part of our natural process, and everyone is entitled to the satiety of this body. This process is not only easily disturbed for PTSD, Anxiety Disorders but also changes the underlying rules of our human nature. Combined with the evil powers of insomnia and migraine is a destructive demon. A demon that could easily slip into depression. Let’s Boil Down.</p> <h2 id="the-struggle"><strong>The Struggle</strong></h2> <p>This is what was described in a note from a friend after all the occurrences of similar experiences with sleep and anxiety.</p> <ul> <li>Your body does not feel you. You feel the discomforting negative vibrating energy in your body.</li> <li>You can’t sleep straight, something keeps poignant and gives you a tight jerk if you try sleeping.</li> <li> <p>There are constantly people in your head waiting for you when you’re in bed and creates thousands of pictures in a second.. Someone speaking to you loudly at the same time… you slide off the bed, you keep moving side to side.. Try to open the eyes the effect stays the same.. you get up it stops.. but there’s a pain in your hands now. Then the only thing that gets me distracted is typing this thing out… But the pain is there, and it won’t allow me to sleep… Either you feel too cold or too hot to run away from the room. There is no comfortable position at all. You can’t sit anywhere; it feels trembling… You can’t sleep, listen to music, listen to the meditation, let alone use this time of not sleeping to my advantage. Regardless you try again somehow you can access the conscious part of sleeping in your brain and send a signal to your body to sleep again, try again, and so we try. Sleeping straight, relaxed, taking deep breaths like in yoga Nidra or deep relaxation meditation, which with practice you become good at. You sleep that way, and just when you thought you drifted apart, and you’re going to sleep, and the nightmare is ending.. it gives you a jerk… I get the hip bone jerk and multiple times enough to get me off that position into turning myself on the back and my hands underneath my thighs, locking myself completely ..pushing my body with hands tied onto the bed. It feels suitable for a few seconds until it realizes. The side to side neck rotation exercise starts like in a horror movie the ghost looks left-right quickly that’s what you do here… bang your head left to right to find a comfortable posture but that is a trap, set for me to come out of the hand locking position.. that worked. I felt very exhausted ..and I thought exhausted I’d finally get sleep, but they play their final card.. it gives some signals to the shoulders, and the joints start banging to the bed one by one left and right until it finally releases me from my lock. I’m back to square one…the mind is alert subconsciously, and I’m trying to fool it… You’re back to counting something, weird characters whose image never forms up, your chest jerks, and the constant hands and legs pain never really allows for a night of sleep. The night until 5.30-6am in the morning when the time seems nice and fresh..you get a 30min nap just to protect you from hallucinating. It actually tricks the brain again that it has slept by sleeping at a time you feel you’ve slept. It was very scary when my friends told me I had gone outside in the garden in the middle of the night.</p> <blockquote> <p>“But nothing feels me or my body.. I don’t know where we are or what they want..all we want is sleep.. which the demons will never gift us.” - My Friend</p> </blockquote> </li> </ul> <h2 id="tried-tested"><strong>Tried, Tested.</strong></h2> <p>Have you Tried and Tested or Tasted or Experienced everything, every law in the universe? But it turns out there is no set law that is helping people come out of this without medications, meditation, CBT, all kinds of therapies, and love. All without assurity of it working. Does love help? Heard of how a person of any gender changed completely after marriage or after finding love?</p> <p>Heard of how a person of any gender changed completely after marriage or after finding love?</p> <p>Love had somehow interfered with how you are made and made some changes to stay according to rules of love so to make a healthy relationship possible. It might have changed your neural circuitry and possibly made you into a better person.</p> <p>Imagine a friend who also feels more like your brother, and you care for him that way too. Now this person has it all - anxiety, insomnia, migraine combined with an overimaginative, overthinking, and a brilliant mind. The friend comes to you and tells you that he might have a Bicameral mind. The anxiety is both of them. There is no me at those times. There is absolutely zero control.</p> <p>You try to comfort him saying everything will be alright, just try sleeping early and get rid of your bad habits(ain’t much) - you give ridiculous, but caring suggestions which you think will work just fine. You tell them to take medications, have a disciplined sleep schedule, stop overthinking(haha),</p> <p>My Favorite - If you can’t sleep at night why don’t you use that time to study or learn something - I bet you could use the extra time, we people don’t get enough time to learn- you’re lucky. Meditation all that.</p> <p>These suggestions are very caring but stupid. Even talking to a therapist who specializes in CBT(Cognitive Behavioral Therapy - More on this next time) suggested some tricks, formulas, reward functions to give yourself from time to time and to not let it distract to put in simple terms.</p> <p>To keep in control, meditation isn’t getting you anywhere permanently as well. The friend tried for 3 days, and 1 day he magically fell asleep for 5-6 hours. It’s the maximum that the person had ever got during the last 3-4 months. The results are encouraging, and every day he goes through permutations to see if this would work to let him somehow sleep today, and in turn, he tries all of the things which again disturbs the mind. One day I decided to send an audio note to my friend, who included me singing a stotra slowly from Sikhism(The mool mantra), and that helped him sleep magically. He woke up and told me to keep sending… it worked for another day with the same note though.</p> <p>I kept thinking why does this help him sleep after listening to it repeatedly, is he trying to bore his brain to death? That’s what his solution is or has he found love which was in the audio, and he felt it.. felt loved by a brother, and he felt an intimate connection, had someone to support him. Turns out love does work- but only sometimes. There were times when he tried very hard even when sleeping on my lap for hours with me singing him soft kitty from the big bang theory - he would get short naps, but I was just delighted to at least give him that, give that much relief to the sufferings endured by him. I do realize it now coz it’s happened to me, but he taught me how to handle it, how to fool it even when you’re not in control. You don’t fight it. Anxiety will always win.</p> <p>This is what it might look like if imagined -</p> <p>This is gibberish text which is just less letter spacing - I mean in negative pixels. This is what it is like in images.</p> <p>The anxious mind tries to decipher this in an unending cycle. Personally, When you feel all that described in Struggle, One can only really feel it when you yourself feel it. No books, no articles, no person can demonstrate how anxiety looks like. There have been significant efforts made my Nicky’s blog with her crazy animated storyNcase, but none have come close. Even if you were given a person to observe and calculate their behavior overtime on sleep, social, or any anxiety-inducing task, you would, to a certain extent, come up with a series of patterns based on your judgment through their actions. Still, it would all come down to you actually experiencing it. But how can you do the streamlining of thoughts, overthinking, insomnia, animation, imagination all into one single tiny magical head of yours- possible downloading our brain and transferring a copy into yours - NeuraLink could help. But Oh, we are far, far away. Is there any other way to look at anxiety? I still encourage y’all to come up with solutions that you think are helpful and mail it to nilesh@augle.ai</p> <h2 id="how-to-be-ready"><strong>How to Be Ready?</strong></h2> <p>That people are there for you, you’re not in this alone.</p> <p><strong>Our Podcast</strong> The Sneaky Freaky PodcastAI Existential Crisis</p> <p><strong>Recommended apps -</strong></p> <ul> <li>Slowly(send letters to like-minded amazing people)</li> <li>Turing AI app(Curated youtube tutorials)</li> </ul> <p><strong>Documentaries to watch -</strong></p> <ul> <li>Cowspiracy</li> <li>Heal on Netflix</li> <li>SPECIAL MENTION TV SHOW - Westworld (nothing better exists for me.. nothing)</li> </ul> <p><strong>Music -</strong></p> <ul> <li>Hooverphonic old concerts</li> <li>Michael Schulte- Someone</li> <li>Time after Time (Iron &amp; Wine)</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog-posts"/><category term="brain-posts"/><category term="psychology"/><category term="anxiety"/><category term="brain"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What it means to understand our wiring and anxiety]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Moving Vehicle</title><link href="https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2020/code/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Moving Vehicle"/><published>2020-01-22T15:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-22T15:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2020/code</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2020/code/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="pre-communication">Pre-Communication</h1> <p><br/></p> <h1 id="welcome-again">Welcome again,</h1> <p>To come here you raised a lot of questions in your body, your atoms aligned in a way that is so unique that it won’t happen again. Your brains working in perfect sync, each neuron firing and forming 1000 different connections with other neurons individually and giving you the superpower to see, hear, sense, etc. To visualize the world in your way and to read this article.</p> <p>Jogging 2 rounds along a long park near my backpackers in the evening, my legs responding to the football session I had very early morning in the cold and unsafe air in Bangalore, I go back to a moment where I was cycling on the marine lines bridge along the coast in the heavy rains and high tides in Mumbai and my friends trying to challenge me for a race, I thought how much has changed now.</p> <p>Coming back to my football match, I’m living in the game when these thoughts crossed, and suddenly the ball dribbles through my legs and onto the center forward. I fall back, the forward has a clear shot and manage to put my leg just in time and ball is out for a corner, Sitting in the corner of the park, I come back from the reflections of the day onto the ongoing people in the park - laughing, jumping, cycling in the park gym, small kids with their parents enjoying the slides. At the same time, some girls keep calling the cute kids to come to them while the kid is trying too hard to ignore them. A group of elderly people the ages of our fathers gather around a round seating of broad garden chairs, gossipping the best they can as they laugh, talk and communicate freely with tea glasses in their hands. I think about how much communication makes a person happier or relieved.</p> <h2 id="to-communicate">To-Communicate</h2> <p>A rickshaw driver treasuring everything he has under the seat and locks it and sleeps there in that small cubicle A handcart man after a long day of labour with his naturally built body without the gym sleeps on the handcart without having any roof over his body nor a good blanket and no mattress(just a bedsheet), and somehow they arrange a pillow and laugh with other people over a cup of tea again.</p> <p>Sinking back into my hostel’s cozy sofa in the common room where I sit and observe while listening to songs with an ancient Armenian history book in my hand, a guy named Chris, who happens to be a part-time historian asked me about the book. We discussed the Bourbons of Bhopal, how Jodha Akbar never existed, about historical monuments in Rajasthan, how Bollywood destroys places. All the perks from just having a book in your hand, without even initiating the talk &amp; we went on a book shopping date.</p> <p>Imagining how lives could be better by talking. It’s a hot sunny day sitting inside a bus wishing I had carried the pollution mask with me, the conductor moving barely through the space between the crowded line of people standing and selling tickets to everyone, one boy out of nowhere offered the biscuits he opened, another day, one guy asked in Kannada if he had lunch, as it was already lunchtime. My stop was the last, and by that time everyone had got down, he sat beside me, I asked basic things like how many rides you take daily, the myth revolving around KSRTC bus drivers driving drunk, I still think they do, reaching another level of dangerous rides from Wadala drag racers to Ksrtc overtakers, praying to God(alltheist at the moment) to come out alive &amp; someone saying the cliche ‘zinda jaana hai bhai.’ The point with talking is that someone is there to listen to you, so when he was chatting, he found relief, when you get them out of their zone, of their usual ticket-ticket game and ask them as a human and treat them like one.</p> <p>Now there is a person besides you or in front of you who may have some knowledge of something you may haven’t heard of, and you could talk to them, about shows, books, religion, places, family, passion, all you have to do is just ask, seek interest, learn what they think of a mutual topic. These small things people do remember, some even become friends for years. Think of how you and your best friend met? Or any of your friends met, totally random, weirdly strange way, wasn’t it? This is what every solo traveller has advised me. They’ve been to the snow, mountains, places, experienced cultures, history, people, but they say this one thing - we go solo, not come alone. Nothing’s planned, take that random conversation road and then see where your destiny takes you. People are amazing, the best things, more variety than food. Also, not all connections are real, overhearing the conversation as my friend puts it on loudspeaker (a friend on the other end)</p> <p>Friend1: Hey bro, did you get the job? Friend2: Daaruu!! That connection came through, and I got the job. Friend1: Don’t know about you but my links get me an extra pani-puri(Indian snack)</p> <p>This would just be using that person for your advantage. Still, if you know the person well, you would be telling them to help you instead of asking for a favour :D, I won’t encourage to get to know all the people, don’t creep out people, have a genuine interest in knowing about other’s lives and how they live it to better understand yours and improve, grow otherwise don’t spoil their solitude,aloneness. Observe things &amp; situations and adapt to it. But don’t copy anyone–nothing from your heroes, idols, mentors, cool friends. Be yourself. Communicate. Question.</p> <h2 id="question">Question</h2> <p>Have you questioned everything, every law in the universe? How the power of sounds &amp; smell work wonders with your memory &amp; emotion, why the abcd, why the heck math, why cruel people exist? If you’re not, you’re on vacation, or you have stopped working on yourself and the hunger to know things is dying. How does smell trigger memories? I remember a perfume from one of my oldest friends, the shampoo on her hair which triggers back her memories, mostly it’s the first time smell that is associated with that person and stored deeply differently as they are not stored where the visual, touch or audio inputs are stored and processed, they take their time to process. Visual &gt; audio In an Olympic race, they use guns and no visual screens to show to start the race cause perhaps those little milliseconds can make a big difference in a country’s tally of medals. The smell is not only stored deep in memory in the amygdala but also linked to emotions. Perfume makers use this. People who want to feel attracted to others wear it. But we also label smells as powerful, strong, beautiful for love, and some are just sick, pungy, gasping for air.</p> <h2 id="answers">Answers</h2> <p>Now when you talk about questioning, you also speak about answering for other questions, contributing to this world in matters that you have enough knowledge and support the right people doing the good things. Help in the sustainable goals, in reducing global warming, in eradicating hunger, violence(all kinds). We do spend billions in space missions, but we do not spend much on successfully providing meals to the hungry who depend on crowdfunding or big foundations. Also begs the question - is discovery more important than fulfilling the stomach? Beware of the information you receive, verify it and no Einstein wasn’t bad at math ever and also waving your phone around for network does not get you good signal only makes it worse, makes you look like an idiot and no there are not just 5 human senses but 9, your whole life is a lie. This article is all about making the world a better place Well, whenever I think of writing and look back at my previous 2 articles, god I was an amateur. Still, then I understand how we feel about old chats and when you see them, you can’t really believe if that person was you, or old voice recordings that really make me laugh hysterically. I write a lot with a pen &amp; paper, It all soon will come out in the form of me reviewing books and story reading. It’s like movie scripts, so what good would it do sitting in my books? Some recommendations you’d like - Flow by Mihali Csikszentmihalyi Here (can you pronounce his name?) TV Link (Podcast about finance, investment and management, interesting talks) and the biggest podcast ever - NPR (gotta listen to this) Recommended apps - Castbox (listen to podcasts) Ablo (chat &amp; learn languages) Anybooks (read please) Down dog (Yoga please) eye care plus (Do some eye exercises will you?) kickstarter (new tech prototypes,ideas) money manager (you will save money when you record it) sky map(if your the telescope guy) Documentaries to watch - BBC the human face series Genius series Tesla- Master of lightning The Wall Street code Cosmos and Planet earth series Music - mad about you by hooverphonic yeh pal - prateek kuhad</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog-posts"/><category term="emotions"/><category term="brain"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Improvement, Smell, Emotions and Human life in a vehicle. (Jan 22, 2020)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thinking out louder - First blog</title><link href="https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2019/first-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thinking out louder - First blog"/><published>2019-06-07T15:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-07T15:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2019/first-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nilesharnaiya.github.io/blog/2019/first-blog/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-importance">The Importance</h1> <p>It is night time and after a brief period of scorching &amp; sweating summer, the rains have taken over and the wind accompanying them takes the weather to cool heaven. Give me no blankets no pillows and I can still sleep down on the ground feeling the coldness of the furniture or I could sleep outside on the grass of the lively football field and no one would bother me in my sacred space, also reminding me of my village. Sleeping under the stars, under our rugs to scare away the cool air, chatting about ghosts and then argue on who would sleep on the last mattress on either side :)</p> <p>Everyone at many levels in their life has embraced the beauty and liveliness of our mother nature. But are we taking advantage?</p> <h3 id="everest-debris">Everest Debris</h3> <ul> <li>10886.217 Kilograms of Trash</li> <li>4 Human Bodies found over last 2 months (Apr-May 2019)</li> <li>In the first half, death toll seems to be 11</li> </ul> <p>Clearly, we are not safe from nature and neither is nature safe from us. Humans love adventure, so much so that there is overcrowding everywhere where nature is marketed beautifully. Imagine a place you had seen 10 years ago, so alluring and magical and now you visit the same place and people say it is utter garbage would you not be disappointed and would you not want to see what happened to that place and who did it? Aren’t we collectively responsible? Will our future generations be able to explore and look deep into nature if we destroyed it soon enough? Quite Lately I could relate to lady justice with our problems. We are holding the sword representing authority over nature and trying to create a balance while being blindfolded and alert all the time.</p> <p><strong>Source:</strong> PBS</p> <h3 id="intentions">Intentions</h3> <p>Those who love nature at it’s fullest know that there is no good or bad nature. They appreciate it in all forms and do not discriminate with nature. We always had good intentions to explore and learn more about our nature. Intentions can be a fickle business, In the ’30s, Thomas Midgley invented the chemical compound ‘freeon’ trying to do good and was a great invention as it saved lives until the scientific community realized it was causing irreparable damage and ripping holes inside the ozone layer, ultimately dubbing Thomas Midgley as the most destructive scientist ever in history. He was just trying to improve the world around him through science but he was human after all. We have little knowledge to act upon and we continue on our journey of discovery of new ideas and inventions.</p> <h3 id="discoveries">Discoveries</h3> <p>Since the invention of electricity and networking, we have known that anything can be possible to discover. We are just in awe of the beauty of these creations. Who would have thought that you could just swipe and talk to someone from anywhere to anywhere in the world just over the air(Just the damn air?) What isn’t possible. Are we narrow minded to think of the impossible?. Coming to space, as Asimov’s book describes that an advanced race of extraterrestrial life is already ruling over us which is limited in population but are thousand times powerful to wipe the human race on earth at any time and we might be in a simulation controlled by them with their stories put into our minds and after all we may well be Artifical Intelligence and not Humans. But then, paradoxes spoil our fantasy theories and tell us that if time travelers or aliens existed they would have visited us by now. After all, we are just a tiny little planet called earth in this marvelously humongous cosmos.</p> <h3 id="space-debris">Space Debris</h3> <ul> <li>128 million pieces of objects</li> <li>Each piece travelling at a velocity that can destroy any rocket coming in its way</li> </ul> <p>It not only poses a threat to space vehicles but humans as well travelling in the future. As my friend once said - The nature will one day get fed up of us and wipe us all. One thing that disturbs me a lot that only some people will ever learn to respect nature. NASA has taken great measures to avoid accidents from space debris and Switzerland has also sent a janitor satellite to clean up space debris. We have always tried to improve or sort our mistakes, but not resorted to prevent it. If we had kept our oceans clean, we wouldn’t have to take measures to clean it - now we are spending millions and the best minds in cleaning up things. I have seen educated people throw waste on the road. What is the reason? For this, I read few opinions of Quorians and majority had said that it is the problem of attitude in people’s behavior and others have blamed the government for lack of measures in garbage management and awareness and strict laws against littering. It certainly does not encourage me when we talk about attitude and hopes are lost when I think about trying to enlighten people of wrong things because eventually, the mind that controls is the mind that performs the cleaning. When I talk about nature, I talk about everything and not just the trees and mountains but everything in this universe, including our body. We got to take care of it all.</p> <h3 id="colonization">Colonization</h3> <p>I am in favor of colonization and it has been great to explore new lands, and what has been achieved since the 14th century - starting with the Vikings in Norway, Iceland, Greenland. When you notice these people - the explorers and the nomads and the ones working for SpaceX and NASA, they have one thing in common - Madness. The madness that is above all dedication and passion, Madness to discover something impossible - crazy technologies which we might never have heard of because Nasa and other collaborative companies were working on it secretly. Many of my friends interested in tech are scared of what future technology might bring and hell even flying cars creep them out, though we will get used to it and it might just turn out to be like Tomorrowland(2015). I’m not being a pessimist here but want to highlight that our creations have somehow harmed us in some way though we are all excited about what’s to come and it does not include just technology. Technology is fun and I’m not saying to limit your usage and go enjoy nature - we need no harm to the earth we live in. Climate change will kill us all and all of this won’t matter at all. Every invention every person every dream destroyed in an instance and we might have to start from the beginning. Back to dinosaurs then neanderthals tools and again reliving the industrial and agriculture revolution but the people will be different. I believe that everything affects everything just like a simple demand and supply affects the economy of a country. We might find some other earth’s or planets to live sustainably but there are so many concerns. Let’s say we all migrate to Mars in 2030-35 and the earth is destroyed. Our population will kill us first. A growing 8 billion people on a planet which is less dense than our earth and to start everything from the beginning - there will be wars for food, land and just about everything you can think that you had on earth but not on mars and you have to fight for it. It’s not enough on earth and won’t be enough on mars.</p> <h3 id="reflections">Reflections</h3> <p>I am questioning and complaining the whole article but I believe it had to come out of me from my first blog itself and it also reveals something about me and the way I think and my perspective towards the world. I am also part of the problem and have done nothing about it. Only through education and awareness in social media can we bring a change that is worth talking about</p> <p>I will appreciate any feedback you are willing to give - good or bad. My ears are always open for praise, constructive criticism or suggestions for future writings. Please drop me an email at nilesharnaiya@gmail.com after you’ve finished reading this tutorial and let me know what you think… reader feedback is one of the things that makes maintaining a site like this worthwhile</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog-posts"/><category term="psychology"/><category term="environment"/><category term="stats"/><category term="fiction"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[June 7, 2019st - In my debut, I talk about the fights between nature and humanity's inventions, educating people with statistics, images and some fictional thoughts that could be true]]></summary></entry></feed>